# Mehrab Hamidi

M.s. Student at McGill University

Research Assistant at Mila



7 October 1999



Montreal, QC



+1 (438) 979-7859



 $\begin{array}{l} linkedin.com/in/mehrab-hamidi-42025b19 \end{array}$ 



mehrab.hamidi@mail.mcgill.ca, mehrab.hamidi@mila.quebec

# About me —

Experienced data scientist with strong mathematics background and researcher with a demonstrated history of working in the computer software industry. Skilled in Data Science, Python, Java, R, Algorithms, and Research. Strong engineering professional with a Bachelor's degree focused in Computer Science from Sharif University of Technology.

# Interests -

Deep Learning Theory Geometrical Analysis of Deep Relu Networks Optimization Statistical Inference Computational Biology

## Education

since 2022 M.s. in Computer Science McGill University/Mila

Computer Science Department

2017-2022 B.Sc. in Computer Science Sharif University of Technology

Mathematics and Computer Science Department

2018-2022 Minor in Mathematics Sharif University of Technology

Mathematics and Computer Science Department

### Publications |

2023 Predicting Survival of Iranian COVID-19 Patients Infected by Various

Variants Including Omicron from Ct Scan Images and Clinical Data

Using Deep Neural Networks(Helyion)

2023 A New R Package for Categorizing Coding and Non-Coding Genes

(pre-print)

2022 Somatic point mutations are enriched in non-coding RNAs with possi-

ble regulatory function in breast cancer (Nature Communication Biol-

ogy)

2020 Accurate and Rapid Diagnosis of COVID-19 Pneumonia with Batch

Effect Removal of Chest CT-Scans and Interpretable Artificial Intelli-

gence (pre-print)

### Research Experience

Since 2023 Hidden Symmetries of Deep ReLU Networks

This ongoing research explores the function spaces of deep ReLU networks, focusing on uncovering architectural symmetries. The project is a collaborative effort with Dr. Elisenda Grigsby and Dr. Kathryn

Lindsey from the Mathematics Department at Boston College.

2022-2023 Reverse-Engineering Deep ReLU Networks

This project involved the development of techniques to deduce the weights, biases, and architecture of deep ReLU networks solely from

input-output queries, without prior assumptions about their structure.

2020 Likelihood-Free Method for Estimating Trait Phenotype Posterior Dis-

tributions

We aimed to identify causal SNPs and predict phenotypes for specific traits using likelihood-free Bayesian methods. The research also extended to applications in Longitudinal Genome-wide Association Stud-

ies.

2019 Landscape Analysis of Non-Coding RNA in Cancer

This pioneering study introduced an integrative pipeline to analyze the mutational load across non-coding RNA genes in six cancer types, identifying significant cancer-specific mutations. I have authored two of the four papers from this project, with the remaining papers under

review or in preparation for publication.

2019 Enhancing Variable Selection for Categorical Data Using the Knockoff

Method

This study focuses on improving the performance and applicability of variable selection methods for categorical data, specifically through the

enhancement of the Knockoff method.

# Relevant Courses

#### Graduates Courses

- Theory of Deep Learning (2023) - Université de Montréal Ioannis Mitliagkas

Mathematical Tools in Computer Science (2022) - McGill University Prof. David Rolnick

Bayesian Method in Statistics and Learning (2019) - SUT Efron, B., Hastie, T. (2016). Computer age statistical inference (Vol. 5)

Machine Learning (2018) - SUT Bishop, C. M. (2006). Pattern recognition. Machine learning, 128(9).

Convex optimization (Audit) Boyd, S., Boyd, S. P., Vandenberghe, L. (2004). Convex optimization. Cambridge university press.

Deep Learning (Audit)

Advanced Bioinformatics (Audit)

### • Undergraduates Courses

Statistics

Wonnacott, T. H., Wonnacott, R. J. (1969). Introductory statistics.

- Linear Algebra

- Game Theory

Ross, S. M. (1976). A first course in probability (No. 519.2 R6). New York.

- Mathematical Real Analysis

- Information Theory

Operation Research

Artificial Intelligence

Stochastic Process

Lawler, G. F. (2018). Introduction to stochastic processes. Chapman and Hall/CRC.

since 2021 Research Assisstant Intern

Currently working on a project about bayesian inference using likelihood free variational methods

2018-2021 Undergraduate Research Assistant

Involved in several research projects in genomics such as landscape

analysis of non-coding RNAs

2020-2021 Data Scientist AI-Med

DML

McGill University

Provided comprehensive analysis and recommend solutions to address complex medical-related problems and issues using data (mostly image type data) from internal and external sources and applied advanced analytical methods such as DL to assess factors impacting growth and profitability across product and service offerings.

2019-2020 Machine Learning Engineer Fanap

Implemented and evaluated artificial intelligence and machine learning algorithms and neural networks for diverse industries. I worked as a member of team on a project about Automatic Speech Recognition

# Honors and Awards

2017 Ranked 130 among one hundred thousand student attendance in uni-

versity entrance exam (Konkur)

2016 Best poet of the state

2015 Gold medal of national swimming competition and a member of the

university swimming team

2017 A member of the Iranian Mathematical Society. Skills

Languages Farsi/Persian (native)

English (fluent)

TOEFL iBT - November 27, 2021 (Overall: 100)

Reading: 27 - Listening: 28 - Speaking: 23 - Writing: 22

Software Python, R, Java, LATEX, C++

Tools Pytorch, Tensorflow, Scipy, CVX, ggplot, limma

Mathematics Linear Algebra, Variational Inference, Bayesian Statistics, Convex and

Linear Optimization, Probability, Stochastic Processes, Combinatorics,

Graph Theory, Real Analysis

# Other Experiences

• Teacher Assisstant

– Foundations of Programming – Artificial Intelligence (2020)

(COMP202)

McGill University - Fall 2022 – Discrete Mathematics (2019)

– Statistical Machine Learning – Fundamentals of Programming

Reading books

(graduate course) (2020) (2018)

• Teaching Combinatory

National Olympiad in Informatics - since 2018

# Hobbies

Playing Tennis
Watching Movies

• Working out

• Hiking

Mountain Climbing
Playing Violin/Kamancheh

# Refrences

David Rolnick

Assistant Professor, Computer Science at McGill University and Mila Quebec AI

Institute.

McGill University 3480 Rue University

Montreal, QC H3A 2A7 Canada

drolnick@cs.mcgill.ca

Hamid R. Rabiee

Professor, Department of Computer Engineering

Sharif University of Technology

Phone: (+9821) 6600-6399 Fax: (+9821) 6604-7662 rabiee@sharif.edu

Hamid Alinejad-Rokny

Associate Lecturer

UNSW Sydney

Phone: (+61) 2 9385 1725 h.alinejad@unsw.edu.au